A Guide to the Cumming Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6922-aa
Cumming Family Papers 1874-1984
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6922-aa
ca. 1800 items
Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library on May 13, 1985, by the Honorable Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr., of Washington, D.C., and has no restrictions.
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of Ambassador Hugh S. Cumming, Jr. contains ca. 1800 items (4 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear feet), 1874-1984, chiefly correspondence of Hugh and Winifred Cumming and genealogical material. The collection is arranged into four series: correspondence, topical, genealogy, and photographs and printed material.
The correspondence includes: correspondence between Hugh and Winifred Cumming while he was away on diplomatic missions in England, Canada, and Iceland; letters concerning a book,
Recollections of a Childhood in Nottoway
, by Lucy Booth Cumming; and correspondence with St. Paul's Church, Washington, D.C., and the University of Virginia.
In the topical files are papers relating to his diplomatic service, including Indonesian affairs and an interview for the John Foster Dulles Oral History Project.
Families represented in the genealogical material include the Ballentine, Blandy, Booth, Cryer, Epes, Forman, Canabiss, Gholson, Martiau, and Starke families.
The photographs are predominantly those of the University of Virginia Medical Class of 1891-1892 (with members identified) and the past Presidents and Board of Governors at the Metropolitan Club, November 3, 1969.
Container List
- SERIES I: CORRESPONDENCE
  - Correspondence of Hugh and Winifred Cumming, 1937-1956; (2 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - General, 1933-1983; (2 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - Letters re Recollections of a Childhood in Nottoway by Lucy Booth Cumming, 1971-1973; (2 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - St. Paul's Church, Washington, D.C.- Correspondence, 1958-1969 (Box Box 1)
  - University of Virginia Gift Fund- Correspondence, 1972-1983 (Box Box 1)
- SERIES II: TOPICAL
  - Conference on the United States Ambassador, 1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Indonesia n Materials, 1956-1961, 1973-1975 (Box Box 2)
  - The John Foster Dulles Oral History Project- Interview with Hugh S. Cumming, Jr., 1966-1967 (Box Box 2)
  - "The Overlook Property", 1973-1977 (Box Box 2)
  - "The Rebecca Fund", 1970-1978 (Box Box 2)
  - University of Virginia Library Correspondence, 1962-1975 (Box Box 2)
- SERIES III: GENEALOGY
  - Ballentine Family, 1957, 1971-1972, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Blandy Family, 1984 (Box Box 2)
  - Booth, Edwin Gilliam and Robert Henry, 1971 (Box Box 2)
  - Booth Family- Mrs. S.B. Taylor Material, [1971] (Box Box 2)
  - Booth Family Correspondence, 1874-1902 (Box Box 2)
  - Booth Family Genealogy, 1961-1984, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - Booth Family Genealogy - Colonial Dames of America Applications, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Booth Family Material, including copies and transcripts, 1965-1972, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  - " Bothwell" and Blackstone, Virginia Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box Box 3)
  - Cryer Family, 1971-1972, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  - Epes, William Dandridge- Information (Box Box 3)
  - Forman Family, 1971, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  - Genealogical Material for Booth, Canabiss, and Forman Families, 1964, 1971-1972, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  - Genealogy - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1935-1975 (Box Box 3)
  - Papers of Hugh and Winifred Cumming, 1935-1978 (Box Box 3)
  - Gholson Family, 1897, 1965 (Box Box 3)
  - Marriage, Church, and Real Estate Records for Nottoway County, 1746-1815 (Box Box 3)
  - Martiau Family, 1984 (Box Box 3)
  - Starke, William E. and Edward B., 1971 (Box Box 3)
  - Wills, n.d. (Box Box 3)
- SERIES IV: PHOTOGRAPHS AND PRINTED
  - Booth Family and Home Photographs (Box Box 4)
  - Photographs, 1891-1953 (Box Box 4)
  - Printed Material, 1909-1984 (Box Box 4)
- OVERSIZE ITEMS
  - Photograph of " Hawthorne, " Jefferson County, West Virginia, n.d. (Box Oversize)
  - Genealogical Worksheets on the Booth, Epes, and Forman families, 1963, 1971 (Box Oversize)
  - Genealogical Notes on the Booth and Cryer families, 1971 (Box Oversize)